Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 37: Homily [in Honor] of [the Archangel] Michael. Dərəsanä Mika'el, circa 1770-1830; 2 cols., 25 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Three miniatures. Leather case with strap, one end detached. Wooden boards covered with stamped red leather, stit
  - Homily [in Honor] of [the Archangel] Michael, circa 1770-1830; Located on folio 3r-66r. (Unitid 37)
    - Homily on the Family of Astäraniqos and Euphemia, by Yohannəs, Bishop of Aksum, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 46r-51r. (Unitid 37)
    - Miracle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 51r-52r. (Unitid 37)
    - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 52r. (Unitid 37)
    - Hamle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 52r-56r. (Unitid 37)
    - Homily on the Wicked Wealthy Man Whose Property Was Inherited by the Son of His Poor Neighbor [by Bishop Yohannəs], circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 52r-55r. (Unitid 37)
    - Miracle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 55v-56r. (Unitid 37)
    - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 56r. (Unitid 37)
    - Nähase, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 56r-59r. (Unitid 37)
    - Homily on the Book of the Angels that Came from Jerusalem, Author Not Given, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 56r-58r. (Unitid 37)
    - Miracle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 58r-59r. (Unitid 37)
    - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 59r. (Unitid 37)
    - Mäskäräm, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 59r-61v. (Unitid 37)
    - Homily on Not Worshipping Other Gods, Author Not Given, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 59r-61r. (Unitid 37)
    - Miracle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 61rv. (Unitid 37)
    - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 61v. (Unitid 37)
    - Təqəmt, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 62r-66r. (Unitid 37)
    - Homily on the Need to Make the Angels Sureties by Honoring Them, Author Not Given, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 62r-64v. (Unitid 37)
    - Miracle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 64v-66r. (Unitid 37)
    - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 66r. (Unitid 37)
  - Magical Prayer Against Snakes, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 66r. (Unitid 37)
  - First Miracle of Mary, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 67r-68v. (Unitid 37)
    How the Archangel Gabriel announced the Virgin Mary when she was spinning silk yarn for the temple.
  - Magical Prayer Against Eye Disease and the Protection of Cattle, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 68v-69v. (Unitid 37)
    In another hand, fitted around the bottom of the existing text.
  - First Folio of a Gospel of John, circa 1770-1830; 1 item Located on folio 68v-69v. (Unitid 37)
    In another hand, from another manuscript.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 38: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 1 col. [fols. 3r-137r], 22-23 lines; 2 col. [fols. 137v-148v], 22 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Fols. 1r-2v, 149v: Blank. Glossy wooden boards, broken upper and lower boards sewn together. Stitched and open spine. (Unitid 38)
  Illustrations: fol. 3r: Häräg.
  Fol. 148v: Pen trial at the bottom of the second column.
  Illustration: Fol. 149r: Pencil drawing of a man's face.
  Fols. 43v-45v: Psalms 56-59 are misnumbered 55-58.
  Fols. 77v-78r: A folio is missing, text goes from middle of Psalm 96 to middle of Psalm 98.
  Fols. 102v: Psalm 120 is misnumbered 129.
  - Psalms, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 3r-117v. (Unitid 38)
    Fol. 60v: Cross in red and black marking the mid-point of the Psalms.
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 118r-129v. (Unitid 38)
  - Song of Songs, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 130r-137r. (Unitid 38)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1800s; Located on folio 137v-145v. (Unitid 38)
    - Monday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 137v-138r. (Unitid 38)
    - Tuesday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 138r-139v. (Unitid 38)
    - Wednesday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 139v-141r. (Unitid 38)
    - Thursday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 141r-143r. (Unitid 38)
    - Friday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 143r-144r. (Unitid 38)
    - Saturday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 144rv. (Unitid 38)
    - Sunday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 145rv. (Unitid 38)
  - Gate of Light, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 145v-148v. (Unitid 38)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 39: Mystigogia (Təməhrətä Həbu'at), Prayer of the Covenant (Sälotä Kidan), and Rampart of the Cross (Hasurä Mäskäl), 1800s; 1 col. [3r-33v], 12 lines; 2 col. [34r-65v], 18 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Plain wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Fols. 1v-2v, 16v-17v: Blank. Two manuscripts have been bound together, they are in different hands. (Unitid 39)
  Fol. 1r: Pencil scrawls.
  Fol. 18r: The original owner's name was left blank and, in crude hand, the name Gäbrä Maryam inserted.
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 13 Regarding Rampart of the Cross, see Sylvain Grébaut, "Petit (a(oura Masqal." Aethiops, 6me année, no. 1 (1938) 12–13. Strelcyn, British Library, 76; Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 2, pp. 1045.
  - Mystigogia, Təməhrətä Həbu'at, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 3r-16r. (Unitid 39)
  - Prayer for the Covenant, Sälotä Kidan, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 18r-33v. (Unitid 39)
  - Prayer Called Rampart of the Cross, Hasurä Mäskäl (Strelcyn 76.3), 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 34r-56v. (Unitid 39)
  - Magical Prayer Undoing Charms, Hasurä Mäsqäl, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 56v-65v. (Unitid 39)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 40: Psalter. Dawit, 1700s; 1 col. [fols. 3r-114v], 24-25 lines; 2 col. [fols. 115r-128v], 25 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Three miniatures. Leather case without strap. Wooden boards with stamped red leather and cloth insert inside leather cover. Covered spine. (Unitid 40)
  Illustrations: Fols. 3r, 8v, 14r, 20r, 28r, 34r, 38v, 55r, 61v, 66r, 76r, 79v, 88r, 93r, 98v, 109r, 115r, 123v: Häräg.
  Illustration: fol. 1v: Miniature of a mustached man in purple and red. Probably the owner.
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Miniature of King David playing the harp.
  Illustration: Fol. 43v: Miniature of Christ: Crucifixion: One Cross: with the Virgin Mary and John the Evangelist.
  Striking images are atypical of Psalters, but these are not painted over the text, they are original to the manuscript.
  Fols. 1r, 2v: In another hand, information on determining the hours by measuring the shadows of the sun (continued across folios).
  Fols. 2v, 128rv: In another hand, information on when to break fasts (continued across folios).
  Fol. 119v: Missing lines inserted in upper margin.
  - Psalms, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 3r-98r. (Unitid 40)
    Fol. 51r: Cross in black ink, with the words "half of them" in Ge'ez inside, marking the mid-point of the Psalms.
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments (With Musical Notations), 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 98v-109r. (Unitid 40)
  - Song of Songs (With Musical Notations), 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 109r-114v. (Unitid 40)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1700s; Located on folio 115r-123v. (Unitid 40)
    - Monday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 115rv. (Unitid 40)
    - Tuesday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 115v-117r. (Unitid 40)
    - Wednesday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 117r-118v. (Unitid 40)
    - Thursday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 118v-120v. (Unitid 40)
    - Friday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 120v-121v. (Unitid 40)
    - Saturday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 121v-122v. (Unitid 40)
    - Sunday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 122v-123v. (Unitid 40)
  - Gate of Light, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 123v-127v. (Unitid 40)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 41: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), Miracles of Jesus (Tä'ammərä Iyassus), 1700s; 2 cols., 24 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Twelve miniatures. No case. Wooden boards with stamped red leather, stitched and open spine (Unitid 41)
  Illustration: Fol. 2v: Miniature of Christ and the Four Beasts (Creatures). Painted to the corners, but does not cover any original text.
  Illustration: Fol. 10v: Miniature of Saint George slaying the dragon. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 11r: Miniature of the Virgin Mary and the Christ Child with two angels holding up her mantle. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 27r: Miniature of Christ: Crucifixion: One Cross, with the Virgin Mary and John the Evangelist. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 67r: Miniature of resurrected Christ raising up Adam and Eve. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 90v: Miniature of the Ascension of Christ. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 122v: Miniature of Christ and the Pharisees. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 140r: Miniature of Saint Mika'el (?) on throne and with cross. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 170v: Miniature of Saint Täklä Haymanot. Painted to the corners of the folio and over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 197r: Miniature of the Virgin Mary saving a soul from hell. Painted to the corners of the folio but not over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 197v: Miniature of a knight with a sword on a horse and a bloody, dead warrior on the ground. Painted to the corners of the folio but not over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 199r: Miniature of two unidentified saints. Painted to the corners of the folio but not over text.
  Fols. 1r, 2r: Pen trial.
  Fol. 1v: In purple ink, upside down, in a later hand, appears the name "Qes Adämä Ayälä."
  The owner's name appears at the beginning and ending of every miracle as Kənfä Mika'el.
  Fol. 196v: States in the text that the owner Kənfä Mika'el gave the manuscript to the Church of Šaka Yohannəs.
  Fol. 199v: Upside down, in the original hand, the beginning of the Miracle of Jesus on his baptism.
  At the end of each miracle, the scribe has left four blank lines to be filled in later with the concluding hymn.
  References: Re. Miracles of Mary, see references listed for manuscript no. 8. Re. Miracles of Jesus, see Sylvain Grébaut, "Les miracles de Jésus. Texte éthiopien publié et traduit." PO 12 (1919) 551–649 (I); 14 (1920) 767–840 (II); and 17 (1923) 783–854 (III).
  - Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa, With Musical Notation, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 3r-5v. (Unitid 41)
  - Extended Version of Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 5r-6v. (Unitid 41)
  - Miracles of Mary, 1700s; Located on folio 6v-166r. (Unitid 41)
    - First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 6v-12r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Ark of the Covenant came into Ethiopia and how the prophecy about Zion the ark is fulfilled by the Virgin Mary.
      Illustration: A large portion of this Ethiopian miracle covered by paintings (two folios).
    - Prayer to the Virgin Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 12rv. (Unitid 41)
    - Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 13r-14v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary was born to Jacob and Hanna.
    - Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 14v-15v. (Unitid 41)
      The Story of the Infant Mary in the Temple (not in Budge or Herolt).
    - Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 15v-17r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary was annunciated by Saint Gabriel while she was spinning silk.
    - Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 17r-18v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary immaculately conceived Jesus and how Joseph was told about her conception by the Holy Spirit in a dream so that he would not doubt her.
    - Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 18v-19v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary gave birth.
    - Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 19v-21r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary and the Christ child received the wise men and the shepherds of Bethlehem.
    - Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 21r-30r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to Tewoflos the Archbishop of Alexandria and told him about the events surrounding Jesus's birth and the flight of the Holy Family into Egypt (see Timotewos miracle).
    - Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 30r-32r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary accepted the book of her miracles compiled by Saint Hildefonsus [Däqsəyos], Bishop of Toledo (Budge, Mary 1; Strelcyn 15.1.1, 32.16.1; also commonly first in medieval European collections).
    - Tenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 32rv. (Unitid 41)
      How Jesus asked the Virgin Mary about the five lamentations.
    - Eleventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 32v-37v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary gave a child to a family in the country of the Europeans (Afərəng) in the state of the French (Färansa) in and how she saved him from wrongful accusation and a death sentence by hanging (Budge, Mary, 22).
    - Twelfth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 37v-39r. (Unitid 41)
      How Sybil the prophetess saw a vision of the Virgin Mary holding her child within a circle around the sun (not in Budge).
    - Thirteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 39v-42v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Sycamore tree swallowed the Holy Family when they were in Egypt and the bandits tried to rob them.
    - Fourteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 42v-43v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary cursed the people of a certain city in Egypt, while the Holy Family was there, when they treated her with disdain and how the city was swallowed by the ground.
    - Fifteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 43v-44r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary cursed the people of a certain city in Egypt, while the Holy Family was there, when they treated her with disdain and and the people's faces became that of wild animals.
    - Sixteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 44v-45v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary blessed and healed the people of a certain city in Egypt when the king invited her to visit.
    - Seventeenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 45v-48r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Holy Family visited Egypt and blessed Asqetəs and how Jesus caused water to well up from the ground using Joseph's rod.
    - Eighteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 48v-54r. (Unitid 41)
      Homily of Cyril of Jerusalem on the Icon of the Virgin Mary in Sedenəya of Damascus.
    - Nineteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 54r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary caused a stream to reverse course (Budge, Mary, 36).
    - Twentieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 54v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper (Budge, Mary 2; Strelcyn 15, 1.3).
    - Twenty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 55rv. (Unitid 41)
      How Abbas, Bishop of Rome, cut off his hand which had been kissed by a woman when he was celebrating the Eucharist, and how the Virgin Mary rejoined it to his arm (Budge, Mary, 5).
    - Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 55v-56r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the dying scribe Damianus (Budge, Mary, 4).
    - Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 56r-57r. (Unitid 41)
    - Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 57rv. (Unitid 41)
    - Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 57v-58v. (Unitid 41)
    - Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 58v-59r. (Unitid 41)
    - Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 59r-60v. (Unitid 41)
    - Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 60v-61r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary recovered the stolen property of two women called Juliana and Barbara, when they were on pilgrimage to Jerusalem (Budge, Mary, 11).
    - Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 61r-62r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary saved two Muslims from the storm when they called on her name (Budge, Mary, 12).
    - Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 62rv. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary moved a monastery near Jericho to Jericho (Budge, Mary, 13).
    - Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 62v-63v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the eyes of Yohannəs Bäkänəsi, the blind priest in Egypt, by anointing him with milk from her breasts (Budge, Mary, 14).
    - Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 63v-64r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the merchant from Colossae after being shot in the eye with an arrow by pirates (Budge, Mary, 15).
    - Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 64v-65v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary restored the sight of a certain blind girl of Bədərman with her breath and milk (Budge, Mary, 16).
    - Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 65v-66v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary arranged marriages for two poor girls called Martha and Yäwahit (Budge, Mary, 17).
    - Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 66v-67v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary delivered the soul of the scribe who was writing the book of her miracles (Budge, Mary, 18). Miracle has one folio painted over.
    - Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 67v-68r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary delivered from prison a certain man called Giyorgis (Budge, Mary, 19).
    - Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 68rv. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary protected the elderly priest called Qätir (Budge, Mary, 20).
    - Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 68v-69v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary sent Saint George to threaten a Qädi (Islamic leader) for imprisoning a Christian (Budge, Mary, 21).
    - Thirty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 70rv. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed a man with a stone foot (Budge, Mary, 22).
    - Fortieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 70v-71r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the Bishop Märqorəwos of his leprosy (Budge, Mary, 23).
    - Forty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 71v-72v. (Unitid 41)
      How a certain rich man hurled a loaf at the head of a beggar and wounded him, and how the Virgin Mary delivered his soul from the devils (Budge, Mary, 86).
    - Forty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 72v. (Unitid 41)
    - Forty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 73rv. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the blind daughter from the city of Qähar.
    - Fragment of a Miracle About a Certain Priest, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 53v. (Unitid 41)
    - Forty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 73v-74v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the foot of a widow from Harətärom (Budge, Mary, 24).
    - Forty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 74v-75r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary raised the son of a certain man from Capadocia (not in Budge).
    - Forty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 75rv. (Unitid 41)
    - Forty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 75r-76v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the sick deacon by anointing him with her breast milk (not in Budge).
    - Forty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 76v-77r. (Unitid 41)
    - Forty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 77r-79r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the Syrian potter and how he glorified her (Budge, Mary, 35).
    - Fiftieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 79rv. (Unitid 41)
      How Marəqos, King of Rome, fled from his palace for the monastery for the love of the Virgin Mary) (Budge?).
    - Fifty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 80rv. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary saved Qiras the thief.
    - Fifty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 80v-81v. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary commanded a deacon to dig up and rebury in consecrated ground the body of an adulterous deacon from the island of Jericho in the city of Gärisat who was killed by the people) (Budge, Mary, 103, similar to Romances, Cleopatra 9 about Chartres?.
    - Fifty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 81v-82r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary cut out and sewed a garment for Filatawos, a bishop of the city of Sä'id in Upper Egypt (Budge, Mary, 40).
    - Fifty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 82r-83r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to Paricos when Filatawos refused to give him penance.
    - Fifty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 83r-84r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary saved the woman in childbirth from drowning (Budge, Mary, 32; Strelcyn 32.16.31; Bland 2; Romances, Cleopatra 3).
    - Fifty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 84r-85r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anəsətasəyos (Budge, Mary, 27).
    - Fifty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 85rv. (Unitid 41)
      How a certain king from Afəras (France) named Niqodimos recited the Hail Mary his whole life and when he died a tree with Hail Mary written on its leaves sprang from his tomb (Budge, Mary, 38).
    - Fifty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 85v-86v. (Unitid 41)
    - Fifty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 86v-87r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the Bishop to restore a priest called Enədrəyas who knew only the anaphora of the Virgin Mary (Budge, Mary, 102).
    - Sixtieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 87v-88r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary saved from a great snake Eskənədros the Jew from Jerusalem.
    - Sixty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 88v-89r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary saved from death a governor of Ephesus named Armatəyas.
    - Sixty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 89r-91r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary aided in the delivery of a child to an abbess before the bishop came to enquire into the matter (Budge, Mary, 25; Bland 24 also in Vincent de Beauvais (from 1264 AD). Middle of miracle, one folio, painted over.
    - Sixty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 91r-92r. (Unitid 41)
      How the icon of the Virgin Mary bowed and responded to the prayer and the bows of a certain monastery's monks (not in Budge).
    - Sixty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 92r-93r. (Unitid 41)
      How a certain Muslim was converted when he saw oil and Myron from the breasts of the icon of the Virgin Mary.
    - Sixty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 93r-94r. (Unitid 41)
      How the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man and how the church keeper gave his daughter to him.
    - Sixty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 94r-95r. (Unitid 41)